

# Raffaele Vergnani

Transport and environmental policy expert

My background is geography and spatial planning. Gained 8 years of professional experience as officer and analyst in environmental and transport policy sectors, in front-row research, consultancy and tech companies. Worked on 8 projects financed by EU bodies and delivered 10+ targeted studies to the EU Commission, the EU Parliament and the Alpine Convention. Truly enthusiast about sustainable mobility, digital innovations and excited about the radical changes that the whole sector is facing.

vergnanir@gmail.com

+39 348 8892092

Berlin, Germany

in linkedin.com/in/raffaelevergnani

### **SOFT AND HARD SKILLS**

Critical thinking

Communication

Public speaking

Teamwork

Python

Versatiliity

Initiative

EU Project Managemen

Microsoft Office 365

Tableau / Power BI

SQL

ArcGI

### **WORK EXPERIENCE**

# Network Planning Manager - Italy Flixmobility GmbH

03/2020 - 12/2020 Market leader operating international long distance bus and train services.

Accomplishments

- Conducted strategic planning of new long distance bus lines across Italy and beyond.
- Prepared ramp-up / ramp-down scenarios to selected bus lines, as a response to COVID-19 pandemic.
- Performed competitors and policy analysis in the long-distance road transport sector.

## Transport Policy Analyst

### TRT Trasporti e Territorio Srl

Consultancy specialised in economics, mobility planning and transport modelling.

Accomplishments

09/2016 - 02/2020

- Delivered 3 research studies on transport policy issues for the EU Commission and the EU Parliament.
- Completed 6 EU-funded projects focusing on passenger transport and logistics.
- Published +30 articles / case studies on web portals with EU-wide coverage on urban mobility.
- Elaborated concept & project ideas into concrete proposals to be eligible to EU financing.

### **Project Officer**

### European Academy of Bolzano (EURAC)

07/2012 - 08/2016
Private research centre, focused on environmental, energy and policy issues.

Rome, Italy

Milan, Italy

Berlin, Germany

#### Accomplishments

- Co-authored 8 research studies in the field of urban mobility and environmental protection.
- Completed 2 EU-funded projects on transport and tourism in the Alps.
- Scientific advisor for the project "AlpInfoNet" (Alpine Space Programe 2007-2013).
- Appointed as external consultant of the Italian Ministry of the Environment, within the framework of the Alpine Convention.
- Member of the Italian delegation of the Working Groups "Transport" and "UNESCO World Heritage" of the Alpine Convention.

### **LANGUAGES**

Italian
Native or Bilingual Proficiency

French
Full Professional Proficiency

English
Full Professional Proficiency

Limited Working Proficiency

#### **EDUCATION**

### Data Analytics bootcamp

Ironhack

01/2021 - 03/2021

Berlin, Germany

### Executive Master in "Environment, Innovation and Management"

**LUISS Business School** 

11/2015 - 01/2017

Rome, Italy

### M.Sc. Geography and Spatial Planning

University of Bologna

03/2009 - 03/2011

Bologna, Italy

### Visiting Erasmus student

University College Cork

09/2007 - 05/2008

Cork, Rep. of Ireland

### **B.Sc. Geographical Sciences**

University of Bologna

09/2005 - 03/2009

Bologna, Italy

#### **AWARDS**

## Commendations received for the work administered during the Italian Presidency of the Apine Convention (01/2013 - 12/2014)

Italian Ministry of the Environment, Secretariat of the Alpine Convention.

- Commendations obtained by the Italian Under-Secretary of State of the Italian Ministry of the Environment Ms. Barbara Degani.
- Commendations given by the Secretary General of the Alpine Convention, Mr. Markus Reiterer.

### **EU-FUNDED PROJECTS (SELECTION)**

Pan-European survey on new mobility patterns in European cities (10/2019 - 02/2020)

The service contract aimed to provide a comprehensive snapshot of mobility patterns in EU cities. The survey and related studies collect information about new mobility modes (car, bike and e-scooter sharing), the use of public transport, private conventionally fuelled and alternative fuelled vehicles.

Sustainable Urban Mobility Indicators (SUMI) (12/2017 - 12/2019)

A service contract for the European Commission's Directorate-General for Mobility and Transport designed to give technical support for the
identification and the collection of a set of sustainable urban mobility indicators in 50 European large and small urban areas (MOVE/B4/2017-358).

"AlpInfoNet" - Sustainable Mobility Information Network for the Alpine Space (07/2012 - 06/2015)

The project aimed to offer travellers with comprehensive information about sustainable transport modes beyond regional and national borders and to address users through smart channels that provide information when needed. A strategy was elaborated for the dissemination of public transport information and integrated existing information systems to a sustainable mobility information network.

### **VOLUNTEER EXPERIENCE**

### Tourist guide

Municipality of San Martino in Rio (RE)

02/2009 - 07/2014

Tasks

 Performed guided tours in Italian & English for visitors accessing the medieval castle located in S. Martino in Rio (Italy) and the annexed museum of agriculture. Occasional collaboration.

### **INTERESTS**

Tennis

Cycling

Travelling

Hiking

Micromobility

E-mobility

Geopolitics

Finance and Investments